Guide to the Toby Myers Papers
University of Houston Libraries
Toby Myers Papers
1972-2010
1976-1995
02/2010-018
Myers, Toby
1.00 linear feet
Special Collections, University of Houston Libraries
This collection includes the records, correspondence, written works, articles, and photographs that document the life of Toby Myers as a worker in the Battered Women’s Movement. The thirteen series span from 1972 to 2010.
Biographical Information:
Called “the Mother of the Texas Battered Women’s Movement” by the Texas Council on Family Violence, Toby Myers is a longtime advocate, speaker, and licensed clinical social worker who has dedicated her life to the fight against domestic violence. Herself a survivor of domestic abuse, Toby Myers received her bachelor’s and master’s degrees from the University of Texas at Austin before obtaining a doctorate from the University of Houston in 1976. She has served since 1992 on the Jewish Advisory Board of the Faith Trust Institute and remains a therapist in private practice as well as an activist against violence in Jewish households.
Toby Myers is the founder of a group that works to reform the behavior of men who batter. She has presented on the subjects of women’s issues and domestic violence for over three decades at hundreds of workshops and seminars and is an expert witness for women who suffer from Battered Women’s Syndrome and consequently have committed acts of violence against their abusive intimate partners.
For her efforts, Toby has received the Hannah G. Soloman Award from the National Council of Jewish Women, Greater Houston Section, was named a “Woman of Distinction” in 2001 by the Bridge Over Troubled Waters, and in 2010 she received the prestigious Dee Dee Ostfeld Award from Aid to Victims of Domestic Abuse (AVDA).
Access Terms
This Collection is indexed under the following controlled access subject terms.
Genre/Form of Material:
Brochures; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence; Manuscripts (document genre); Photographs; Typescripts
Personal Name:
Myers, Toby
Topical Term:
Abused women -- Care -- Texas; Family violence -- Texas
Acquisition Information
Information of acquisition method not available.
Conditions Governing Access:
Open for research.
Related Materials:
Houston Area Women’s Center Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=351
Nikki Van Hightower Papers http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=304
Toby M. Myers, Deborah D. Tucker, and Maria Jose Angelelli Texas Council on Family Violence Records http://archon.lib.uh.edu/?p=collections/controlcard&id=352
Scope and Contents
This collection includes the records, correspondence, written works, articles, and photographs that document the life of Toby Myers as a worker in the Battered Women’s Movement. The thirteen series span from 1972 to 2010.
All material grouped within a series is chronologically arranged.
Detailed List of Contents
- Personal Correspondence, id124259
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains typed and manuscript correspondence of a personal nature addressed to Toby Myers between 1979 and 2010. One folder holds dated material and the other undated.
  - Correspondence, 1979-2008; id124273 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, undated; id124274 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Creative Works, id124260
  This series is comprised of works written by Toby Myers dealing with her activities in the battered women’s movement as well as personal events. Of particular interest is the eulogy written for Nanette Bruckner.
  - Interview transcripts and printed articles, 1982-2005; id124276 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Professional Development, id124261
  Materials in this series deal primarily with Toby Myers’ teaching positions at The University of Texas Health Science Center in Houston, TX.
  - Correspondence dealing with employment, 1981-2006; id124278 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates, 1985-2006; id124279 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Religious Involvement, id124262
  This series documents the role that Judaism has played in the life of Toby Myers. Correspondence, documents, photographs, clippings, and other printed items illustrate her activities within the faith and how she advocated for the rights of Jewish women and battered wives by participating in Jewish women’s groups and speaking out against what she deemed unfair practices.
  - Clippings and brochures, 1980-1986; id124281 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Work with Jewish Women’s groups: Clippings and brochures, 1978-2008; id124282 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Work against violence in Jewish households, 1986-2002; id124283 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Photographs, id124284 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Advocacy, id124263
  This series documents Toby Myers’ involvement in advocacy with correspondence, testimony transcripts, printed material, and photographs.
  - Correspondence, 1981-2000; id124286 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Testimony transcripts, 1978-1995; id124287 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Printed material, 1978-2008; id124288 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Photographs, Texas Council on Family Violence, id124289 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Photographs, National Center on Domestic and Sexual Violence (NCDSV); National Center Against Domestic Violence (NCADV), id124290 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Public Speaking, id124264
  This series documents Myers’ role as a public speaker. Manuscripts, speeches, letters of appreciation and other printed material serve to highlight her participation at speaking engagements, workshops, and seminars dealing with domestic violence and other women’s issues.
  - Correspondence, 1980-1994; id124297 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1995-2002; id124292 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, undated; id124293 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Workshop narrative, 1976-1993; id124294 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brochures, 1976-1988; id124295 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Speeches, manuscript and typescript, 1987-1995; id124296 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Biographical Material, id124265
  This series follow Toby Myers in print media from 1972-2010.
  - “Who’s Who” applications, 1989-2010; id124299 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Clippings and other printed material, 1972-2010; id124300 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Research Material, id124266
  This series contains clippings by Toby Myers of topics of interest to her, but authored by other people.
  - Clipped articles, 1975-1988; id124302 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Clipped articles, 1989-2010; id124303 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Clipped articles, undated; id124304 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Awards and Recognitions, id124267
  This series shows the awards and honors bestowed upon Toby Meyers from 1981 to 2010. Of particular interest are the photographs and newspaper coverage of the AVDA DeeDee Ostfeld Award for Advocacy that she won in 2010.
  - Letters of congratulation, 1981-2010; id124306 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Awards, invitations, and award announcements, 1984-2010; id124307 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Acceptance speeches, 1981-2010; id124308 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, id124309 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- PIVOT Involvement, id124268
  This series contains correspondence and other typed and printed material related to the PIVOT project (now called Battery Intervention and Prevention Program or BIPP).
  - Correspondence, 1988-1995; id124311 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Printed material, 1980-1998; id124312 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Appreciation Party addresses, 1990-1997; id124313 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Photographs, id124314 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Houston Area Women’s Center (HAWC) Involvement, id124269
  This series contains correspondence and other typed and printed material related to HAWC.
  - Correspondence, 1980-1993; id124316 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Printed material, 1978-1995; id124317 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- In Europe for The International Development Project, 1981-1982; id124270
  This series is made up of two folders that contain typescripts and photographs regarding a year that Toby Myers spent in Europe conducting the International Development Project (IDP) for the Texas Council On Family Violence.
  - Correspondence and trip description, id124319 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographs, id124320 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Miscellaneous Photographs, id124271
  This series contains photographs of Toby Myers, friends, and other notable personages. Of particular interest are the candid photographs of the late Texas Governor Ann Richards (1991-1995).
  - Photographic prints, id124322 (Box 2, Folder 16)